Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Herzog, Anna, 1975 March 13 (Cassette 138, Box 29)
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz at the Workmen’s Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York on March 13, 1975. The interview covers Anna Herzog’s life in Minsk, Russia, her immigration to the United States (US), her involvement in union activities and strikes, and her personal life. Herzog recollects her early life in Minsk, including her father dying when she was three years old; her brother serving as a father figure; Jewish children not being allowed to attend school; wanting to play instead of work; and working for a year in a garment factory on a pedal sewing machine. Her first memories of New York, New York include learning English through friends, and being overwhelmed with the size of New York City. She remembers needing to supply her own sewing machine at her first job; and requiring assistance carrying the sewing machine up and down the stairs. She recalls the differences between garment work in Russia and the United States. She recalls a strike in 1911, during which the workers went on strike for 15 days in order to achieve better pay, better working conditions, and for owner-supplied sewing machines. Herzog’s discussion of her personal life includes meeting her husband and their wedding in Toronto, Canada; having two sons and adopting her sister's daughter; discontinuing work because she was pregnant; and moving to the Workmen’s Circle Home against her son’s wishes.
  - Herzog, Jacob, Undated (Box 15, Shoot-negative 138A-138B)
    Jacob Herzog was born in Austrian Galicia to a large Jewish family. In Galicia he worked as a tinsmith and belonged to an unspecified metalworkers' union. He immigrated to the United States (US) around 1911, where he worked and lived in New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, and Ohio. He worked as a metalworker and was a member of an unspecified building trades union. He married and had two sons.
    This interview was conducted at Jacob Herzog’s home on Amsterdam Avenue in Manhattan, New York. The interviewer and date are unknown. Main topics include Herzog’s life in Austrian Galicia; his education in the United States (US); and his leisure activities, politics, and union activities. Herzog discusses his life in Galicia, including working as a tinsmith with his father; belonging to an unspecified metalworkers' union; and his father warning him not to join the Army. He recalls learning English in the US through a librarian who would give him books in both Yiddish and English; and attending night school. He discusses leisure activities in which he participated, including going with his children to the park, beach, and baseball games in Brooklyn, New York; having season tickets to the Metropolitan Opera for 35 years; and enjoying attending symphony concerts. Herzog recalls knowing very little about politics upon his arrival to the US; quickly coming to dislike the Republican Party because they represented the rich; and being a member of the Socialist Party of America for most of his life. He discusses his involvement with an unspecified building trades union; his election as a trustee for his New York local; his service on the examining board; and his belief that every worker should be a member of a union.
    Jewish socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Higgins, John, 1974 (Box 17, Cassette 228B)
    John Higgins was born in New Ross, County Wexford, Ireland in 1887 to a large Catholic family. He immigrated to Australia in 1908 and then to the United States in 1910. He married in 1922 and had two children, both of whom died in childhood. He was employed primarily as an engineer and laborer and was a member of International Union of Operating Engineers Local 30.
    The interview was conducted in 1974, but the interviewer and location are unknown. This interview covers Higgins’ childhood in Ireland; work experiences in New York, New York; social activities in the Irish community of New York; and his union involvement. Higgins discusses his early life in Ireland, including having a happy childhood; his family owning a small grocery store in New Ross; attending a Christian Brothers school; horseback riding and swimming in a local river before work; working as an accountant for an import/export company in County Wexford; and emigrating from Ireland because he was curious and wanted adventure. He discusses his early experiences in New York, including having no friends or family nearby and living in a community that included Hungarians, Irish, and Germans. His early work experience includes being employed by the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company until he quit because his pay was less than the other employees’. Higgins discusses stealing a hammer, chisel, and wrench in order to work as a mechanic at a shipyard; working as a carpenter in order to make money while on strike at the shipyard; and making good money at the shipyard because he was willing to work long hours and overtime. He recollects being the chief engineer for multiple hotels, including the St. Andrews Hotel in Manhattan for over 22 years; never having problems finding work because other Irish immigrants would always help him; and belonging to the International Union of Operating Engineers Local 30. He recalls drinking at the pub with his friends; having negative feelings about Prohibition; watching Irish football and hurling on Long Island on Sundays; and being a member and secretary of the County Wexford Organization, which met on 59th Street in Manhattan.
    John Higgins' sister, Katherine Higgins, was also interviewed for the New York City Immigrant Labor Project. See also: Higgins, Katherine.
    International Union of Operating Engineers.
  - Higgins, Katherine, Undated (Cassette 228 & 228A, Box 17)
    Katherine Higgins was born into a large Catholic family in New Ross, County Wexford, Ireland in the 1880s. She lived in England and France before she immigrated to the United States (US) in 1933. She worked for the British War Office during World War I, in the United States Army Quartermaster Corps in France after World War I, and as a lady’s companion after her immigration in 1933.
    The interviewer, location, and date of this interview are unknown. This interview covers Katherine Higgins’ early life in Ireland, England, and France; her work during and after World War I (WWI); her world travels; and her religion. Higgins discusses her childhood in Ireland in great detail, including the lives of her eight siblings; inheritance laws and her father’s disinheritance due to his choice of wife; and Higgins’ family home in New Ross. Higgins remembers class distinctions within her community; the education system in Ireland; and her opinion that her life would have been boring had she attended college. She recalls living in England, where she studied to be a teacher and worked for the British War Office during WWI. She discusses the 1916 Easter Rising and its aftermath, including her brother-in-law’s wrongful incarceration for weapons possession; the hunger strike and eventual death of Terence MacSwiney; and the fact that her family supported the revolution but believed that it occurred too late. She discusses her work with the United States Army Quartermaster Corps in France after WWI, designing cemeteries for the reburial of American soldiers, and organizing a chapter of American Gold Star Mothers. She explains that she immigrated to the United States (US) and settled in New York, New York in 1933 because it was the only place she could find work. Her first impressions of the US include her surprise at the bigotry towards the Irish and her amazement at the poor education of American men. Higgins discusses her work as a lady’s companion, including attending the film premiere of Gone with the Wind; visiting some of the Nordic countries, the Baltics, and the Soviet Union; and enjoying the fact that her employer owned a car. She also discusses her religious influences, practices, and ideologies, including the fact that she did not practice Catholicism in the years between leaving Ireland and arriving in the US; her opinion that the French were not devout Catholics; that she attended St. Patrick’s Cathedral in Manhattan; and the Irish fear of the afterlife.
    Higgins' brother, John Higgins, was also interviewed for the New York City Immigrant Labor Project. See also: Higgins, John.
    Women household employees |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Hochberg, Eddie, 1975 March 3 (Cassette 112A-B, Box 19)
    Eddie Hochberg was born in Russia to a Jewish family. He immigrated to the United States in 1914, where he was employed in the garment industry. He was a member of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union Local 22, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the United Brotherhood of Cloak Makers Local 1.
    This interview was conducted at the Workmen’s Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York on March 3, 1975 by David Lightner. The main topics include Eddie Hochberg’s life in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US); his work in the garment industry both in Russia and the US; and the internal organization of garment workers’ labor unions in New York, New York. Hochberg discusses his early life in Russia, including his family’s poverty and his father's work as a supervisor in a logging company. He discusses the immigration of his family to the US, including his father immigrating in 1911 and finding work in a paper box factory; two of his brothers immigrating after their father; Hochberg immigrating alone in 1914; and the rest of his family following in 1916. He describes finding his first job through a man with whom he attended synagogue; not being paid for three weeks while he learned the trade; and his first job turning over coats to create seams. He discusses his movement through different factories within the garment industry and his work in each, including manufacturing coats for men, cloaks, and dresses; being paid for both week work and piecework; cleaning and oiling the machines every Friday; working overtime during the busy season; and having to find other employment during the summer. He describes the introduction of labor unions into the garment industry, including the fact that very few companies were unionized initially; the establishment of the National Recovery Administration in 1933 guaranteeing workers the right to join unions; that different locals within the same international union being determined by profession as well as ethnicity; and unions providing benefits such as better pay, vacations, and pensions. Hochberg also mentions that he was a member of multiple unions, including the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union Local 22, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the United Brotherhood of Cloak Makers Local 1.
    International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22 (New York, N.Y.).; United Brotherhood of Cloakmakers.
  - Hoffman, Simon: Audio Recording, Undated (Box 13, Reel 57 (sides 1-2), Cassette 57)
    Simon Hoffman was born in Pilviskiai, Russia in 1893 to a Jewish family. His father worked as a butcher and his mother worked as a wig maker. Hoffman immigrated to the United States (US) through Ellis Island in New York, New York in 1913. He briefly lived with his step-siblings in the Bronx before finding a job as a cap maker. During the Great Depression, Hoffman was employed by the City of New York cleaning public parks. He became a US citizen and a member of the Democratic Party in 1920. He continued to work in the cap making industry until his retirement. He was a member of an unspecified cap makers' union (likely the United Hatters of North America).
    The interviewer, location, and date of this interview are unknown. The main topics discussed include Simon Hoffman’s life in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US) and his early days there; his work in New York, New York; and leisure activities in which he participated. Hoffman discusses his early life in Russia, including the fact that he learned four languages despite not attending school; his work selling sewing notions; and the fact that the Jewish community mixed with other local ethnic groups for commerce but were otherwise segregated. He recalls his family, including the fact that his father was a butcher and was substantially older than his mother; that his mother regretted marrying an older man; his mother’s work manufacturing wigs and hairpieces; and his three siblings. He discusses his immigration to the US, including paying a smuggler 25 rubles to help him cross the border between Russia and Germany; sailing on the SS Bremen from Bremen, Germany; being assisted by the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society after his arrival at Ellis Island, New York; and residing with his step-siblings in the Bronx for a short time before finding work. Hoffman recalls his employment in the US, including making hats on Houston Street in Manhattan; receiving a pay increase during World War I; being employed by the City of New York to clean public parks during the Depression; and resuming his employment in the cap making industry in 1942. He mentions joining an unspecified cap makers' union (likely United Hatters of North America) in 1915, and was proud of the fact that he maintained his union membership after his retirement. Hoffman discusses his leisure activities, including reading the New York Times, the Jewish Daily Forward, and the Jewish Morning Journal; visiting the Hayden Planetarium at the Museum of Natural History in Manhattan; and attending the Jewish theater frequently.
    United Hatters of North America.; Depressions |y 1929 |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Hoffman, Simon: Subject Cards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hoffzimmer, [Unknown], 1973 (Box 3, Reel 18A-18B, Cassette 18)
    The narrator’s first name is unknown. Mr. Hoffzimmer was born in present day Poland in 1896 to a Jewish family. He immigrated to the United States in 1909 and attended public school in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He was employed making human hair goods and Panama hats and opened his own hat manufacturing company before the Great Depression. Hoffzimmer was an active member of the Socialist Party of America and the United Hatters of North America.
    This interview was conducted in 1973 at the Sheltered Workshop of the National Council of Jewish Women in Manhattan, New York by an unknown interviewer. The first name of the narrator is unknown. Mr. Hoffzimmer reminisces about his early life and immigration to the United States (US), including his father being a cobbler; his father not teaching him the trade; and falsifying his immigration papers to show that he was 16 years old in order to emigrate. He discusses the immigration process at Ellis Island, New York, including a required medical examination; the requirement of either $25 or someone to vouch for you; and immigration societies that would vouch for individuals who knew no one in New York and assist them with acquiring lodgings. His first impressions of New York City include not feeling excited about living in New York; the abundance of poverty; and hostilities between ethnic groups, especially between the Jewish and Irish communities. He discusses his involvement with Socialism and the Socialist Party of America, including attending lectures and meetings at the Rand School of Social Science in Manhattan; his feelings about Social Security; society's lack of appreciation for social programs at the time of the interview; and reading the Socialist newspaper The New York Call. Hoffzimmer discusses his family, including meeting his wife through friends; and sending his daughter to the Workmen’s Circle to learn about Jewish language and culture. He discusses his great appreciation for his wife; and the accomplishments of his grandson. He recalls his work experience, in particular finding employment as a hatter through his work manufacturing human hair goods. He describes traveling to the western US and to Mexico with the money he saved at his first job. He recounts learning Spanish and opening a business selling portraits while in Mexico; and opening his own hattery upon his return to New York with the money he made. He also recalls not requiring government assistance during the Great Depression because of his business; discusses the benefits and drawbacks of modernization; and discusses his membership in the United Hatters of North America.
    United Hatters of North America.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.; Jewish socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Howard, Clara, Undated (Box 29)
    Clara Howard was born in Hampton, Virginia 1895. She was one of ten children. Her mother managed the household and her father was farmer and firefighter. Her husband was born in a rural part of Virginia. He served in the United States Navy, worked for the United States Postal Service, and owned a jewelry and watch repair business in White Plains, New York. They married in 1912 and had three children.
    This interview was conducted by Edmund Lake at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York on an unspecified date. The interview covers Clara Howard’s early life in Hampton, Virginia; her family; and her opinions on racial discrimination and civil rights in the United States. Howard discusses her education at the Gray School of the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute in her hometown, which she attended through the tenth grade. She describes her family’s home and explains that although they lived on a farm, they were near large cities, including Newport News and Norfolk, and did not live in an isolated area.
    Howard explains that her older sisters migrated to New York and New Jersey and that she decided to migrate to New York when she was 16 years old after visiting. She recounts living on 139th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan with her sisters in 1912; explains that African Americans were starting to move into Harlem at that time; and describes Harlem as beautiful, brightly lit, and clean. She compares the living situation of minorities in downtown Manhattan to those in Harlem and her belief that the conditions downtown were more primitive than those in Hampton. She compares her children’s education to her own and discusses her opinion that she received a much better education as her teachers were black, took great interest in their students, and served as role models. She recounts an incident of racial prejudice one of her children experienced, her reaction to it, and her feeling that this exemplified the failing of the educational system in New York.
    Howard discusses Marcus Garvey, Father Divine, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Malcolm X, and describes them as great men. She recounts attending services and lectures at the Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem. She discusses black empowerment, including black leaders encouraging the people to pull themselves up but not providing them with the tools to do so and her feeling that most people lack the desire for education. She describes her pride in her education; her willingness to defend herself and family against racial discrimination and injustice; her amazement at the fact that so few people in her community were unwilling to make a similar stand; and her willingness to die for her beliefs.
    Howard discusses her husband’s first job with the United States Postal Service (USPS); the racial segregation within the USPS that led to his unhappiness; and his decision to start his own business. She discusses her husband’s jewelry and watch repair business in White Plains, New York, including the fact that the majority of his customers were white; his belief that his religious faith had enabled him to open his own business; and her management of the shop after he was injured in a car accident.
    Other topics include leisure activities and holidays; theaters in Harlem, including the Alhambra; and Howard’s enslaved grandparents who fled their owners before their two oldest children could be sold away from them.
    See also: Council Workshop for Senior Citizens II.
  - Hyman, Bella: Audio Recording, Undated (Box 13, Records-box 59A-59B, Cassette 59)
    Bella Hyman was born in a small town in Austria in the late 1890s. She was one of nine children. Her parents owned a small grocery store, her father studied in the synagogue, and her mother catered events in the town. Hyman immigrated to the United States (US) in 1913. Her parents and two of her brothers immigrated to the US in 1921.
    She worked in the garment industry in the US, as a hand sewer and finisher. She was a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union). She married in 1923 and had one son. Her husband was born in Russia and immigrated to England when he was young. He was educated in England and was a lecturer. In the US, he was a manager of an unspecified union local. He died in 1940. She and her husband belonged to the Socialist Party of America and the Workmen’s Circle.
    This interview was conducted by Janice Albert. The date and location of the interview are unknown. The interview covers Bella Hyman’s childhood in Austria, her working life in the United States (US), and her union activity.
    Hyman discusses attending night school in the US; participating in organizing garment factories for the union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union); and wishing she could have continued her education but having to work in order to pay for her parents’ immigration to the US. She recounts her childhood in a small town in Austria, including her education and her father studying in the synagogue while her mother managed the family’s grocery store and catered events in the town. She describes her and her siblings’ immigration to the US; their consolidation of their savings in order to pay for their parents’ immigration; and the family’s struggles during the Great Depression.
    Hyman discusses her life in New York, New York after her immigration, including gaining experience in garment factories through different jobs, and moving between different Jewish neighborhoods in Manhattan, Brooklyn, and the Bronx. She recounts wanting to become a nurse; starting a training program at Beth Israel Hospital in Manhattan; and having to leave the program because it did not pay enough for her to contribute to her parents’ immigration. She discusses attending night school and lectures at the Rand School of Social Science in Manhattan; being inclined towards the Socialist Party of America; and finding time to attend dances and sporting events. She describes the ethnic demographics of the workforce in the garment industry, in particular, the fact that the workers were mostly Jewish, Italian, and Polish, which led to language issues while organizing the factories into an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union). She describes the daydreams the garment workers would share with each other and the songs they sang while they worked, but states that these hopes did not preclude their participation in unionizing efforts in order to improve working conditions.
    Other topics include her work visiting retired union members; the movement of the garment industry from the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan to 7th Avenue in the Midtown neighborhood of Manhattan; her husband’s background; and women in leadership roles in unions, specifically Rose Pesotta and Pauline Newman.
    See also: Ethnicity; and Family.